Guide to the Bob Johnson Papers, 1949-2003 CTC.2014.03
ULS Archives & Special Collections
- Black Arts Movement Performing Arts Scripts and Ephemera, 1966-1990; VII.
  - Company Ephemera, 1966-1983; 3.
    - Poster, Black Horizon Theatre (Oversize), ca. 1971 (Map-case 25-6, Oversize 3)
      Scope and Contents
      This poster is advertising performances of Death of Malcolm X by Imamu Baraka and Mojo by Alice Childress at the Selma Burke Art Center.
    - Choreo-Mutation
    - Chuck Davis Dance Company, 1971-1975 (Box 10, Folder 27)
    - Clyde Morgan, 1976-1978 (Box 10, Folder 28)
    - Dance Black America, 1983 (Box 10, Folder 29)
    - Poster, A Dance Dedication to the Late Thelma Hill (Oversize), 1979 (Box 14, Folder 28)
    - Poster, Dance Extravaganza at Veterans' Auditorium (Oversize), 1975 (Box 14, Folder 29)
    - Darlene Blackburn Dance Troupe (Box 10, Folder 30)
    - Dayton Contemporary Dance Company, 1972-1973 (Box 10, Folder 31)
    - Detroit Co-Op. Dance Company (Box 10, Folder 32)
    - Dimensions Dance Theater (Box 10, Folder 33)
    - Eleo Pomare Dance Company, ca. 1959-1971 (Box 10, Folder 34)
    - Poster, Eleo Pomare (Oversized), 1974 (Map-case 25-6, Oversize 1)
    - Poster, The Fred Benjamin Dance Company (Oversized), 1974 (Map-case 25-6, Oversize 1)
    - George Faison Universal Dance Experience, 1974 (Box 10, Folder 35)
    - Glen Brooks Third World Movements (Box 10, Folder 36)
    - Glen Brooks Third World Movements Poster (Oversized) (Box 14, Folder 30)
    - Jamaica National Dance Theatre Company, 1969-1970 (Box 10, Folder 37)
    - Poster, Karamu Performing Arts Theatre (Oversize), 1995 (Map-case 25-6, Oversize 1)
    - Poster, Keith Jarrett (Oversize), ca. 1975 (Box 14, Folder 31)
    - Poster, Langston Hughes House of Kuumba (Oversized), ca. 1971 (Map-case 25-6, Oversize 1)
    - Poster, National Council for Culture and Art, Inc. (Oversized), 1986 (Map-case 25-6, Oversize 1)
    - Posters, Negro Ensemble Company (Oversized), 1969-1970 (Map-case 25-6, Oversize 3)
    - Poster, New Art Ensemble (Oversize), ca. 1970 (Map-case 25-6, Oversize 3)
    - Poster, Nutcracker (Oversize), ca. 1975 (Box 14, Folder 32)
    - Poster, Ode to Ethiopia, multi-media workshops (Oversize), 1981 (Box 14, Folder 33)
    - Otis Sallid's New Art Ensemble (Box 10, Folder 38)
    - Poster, Phoenix Dance Company (Oversize), 1991 (Map-case 25-6, Oversize 3)
    - Poster, Saastras (Oversize), 1974 (Box 14, Folder 34)
    - Raymond Sawyer Dance Company, 1966 (Box 10, Folder 39)
    - Posters, Raymond Sawyer Afro-American Dance Experience (Oversize), ca. 1973 (Box 14, Folder 35)
    - Sounds in Motion (Box 10, Folder 40)
    - Poster, The Stanze Peterson Dance Theatre, Inc. (Oversize), 1973 (Map-case 25-6, Oversize 1)
    - Poster, Uhuru In Art Outdoor Exhibition (Oversize), ca. 1972 (Box 14, Folder 36)
  - Programs, 1966-1987; 4.
    - Ain't Supposed to Die a Natural Death, Ethel Barrymore Theatre, October 1971 (Box 10, Folder 41)
    - Alvin Ailey, 1974-1976 (Box 10, Folder 42)
    - Arthur Hall Presents Orpheus, Shubert Theatre, 1973 (Box 10, Folder 43)
    - Balm in Gilead, Circle Repertory Company, June 1972 (Box 10, Folder 44)
    - Les Ballets Africains, Ethel Barrymore Theatre, November 1966 (Box 10, Folder 45)
    - A Ballet Behind the Bridge, Negro Ensemble Company, 1972 (Box 10, Folder 46)
    - Black Expo, New York City Center, April 1969 (Box 10, Folder 47)
    - Blues for the Gospel Queen, Billy Holiday Theatre, ca. 1977 (Box 10, Folder 48)
    - Blues in the Night, Rialto Theatre, July 1982 (Box 10, Folder 49)
    - The Blood Knot, Pittsburgh Public Theater, 1978 (Box 10, Folder 50)
    - Bubbling Brown Sugar, Heinz Hall, 1977 (Box 10, Folder 51)
    - The Colored Museum, New York Shakespeare Festival Public Theater, June 1987 (Box 10, Folder 52)
    - The Dream on Monkey Mountain, St. Marks Playhouse (Box 10, Folder 53)
    - Do Lord Remember Me, American Palace Theatre, 1982 (Box 10, Folder 54)
    - Don't Bother Me I Can't Cope, 1972-1975 (Box 10, Folder 55)
    - Dreamgirls, Heinz Hall, June 1986 (Box 10, Folder 56)
    - Eubie, Heinz Hall, 1979 (Box 10, Folder 57)
    - Eyes of the American, Negro Ensemble Company, December 1985 (Box 10, Folder 58)
    - The Fabulous Miss Marie, New Locust Theatre, 1971 (Box 10, Folder 59)
    - Fences, Yale Repertory Theatre, 1985 (Box 10, Folder 60)
    - For Colored Girls Who Have Considered Suicide When the Rainbow is Enuf, ca. 1975-1978 (Box 10, Folder 61)
    - Guys and Dolls, Broadway Theatre, August 1976 (Box 10, Folder 62)
    - Here is Josephine Premice (Box 10, Folder 63)
    - Home, Cort Theatre, August 1980 (Box 10, Folder 64)
    - House of Flowers, Theatre De Lys (Box 10, Folder 65)
    - Jelly's Last Jam, Virginia Theatre, July 1993 (Box 10, Folder 66)
    - Joe Turner's Come and Gone, Yale Repertory Theatre, 1986 (Box 10, Folder 67)
    - Kinjeketile, Tanzania National Drama Troupe, June 1977 (Box 10, Folder 68)
    - Lost in the Stars, Imperial Theatre, May 1972 (Box 10, Folder 69)
    - Ma Rainey's Black Bottom, Cort Theatre, 1984 (Box 10, Folder 70)
    - Me and Bessie, October 1975 (Box 10, Folder 71)
    - My Sister, My Sister, Little Theatre, May 1974 (Box 10, Folder 72)
    - Novella Nelson, National Black Theatre (Box 10, Folder 73)
    - Ousmen, Second World African Festival of Arts and Culture (Box 10, Folder 74)
    - Purlie, ANTA Theatre, ca. 1971 (Box 10, Folder 75)
    - Raisin, Syria Mosque, 1976 (Box 10, Folder 76)
    - A Raisin in the Sun, American Kaleidoscope Inc., 1984 (Box 10, Folder 77)
    - Sarafina!, Benedum Center for the Performing Arts, January 1991 (Box 10, Folder 78)
    - Stories About the Old Days, New Federal Theatre (Box 10, Folder 79)
    - The Taking of Miss Janie, Mitzi E. Newhouse Theater, May 1975 (Box 10, Folder 80)
    - What the Wine-Seller Buys, ca. 1974 (Box 10, Folder 81)
    - The Wiz, ca. 1976 (Box 10, Folder 82)
    - Your Arms too Short to Box with God, Heinz Hall, ca. 1979 (Box 10, Folder 81)
    - Zora and When the Chickens Came Home to Roost, New Federal Theatre, ca. 1981 (Box 10, Folder 82)
- Audio/Visual Recordings, 1969-1985; VIII.
  The audio/visual recordings of the Bob Johnson Papers include examples of his performing career as well as his teaching at the University of Pittsburgh. The recordings in this series have been digitized from the original media as a part of a project funded by a Recordings at Risk grant from the Council on Library and Information Resources. The series is divided into two subseries, one for audio recordings and another for film and video. Both subseries are arranged chronologically.
  - Audio, 1969-1985; 1.
    The types of recordings in this subseries include concerts, interviews, music accompanying performances, lectures, performances, radio broadcasts, and rehearsals. These audio recordings are arranged in chronological order.
    - Dancemobile Rehearsal, Harlem Cultural Council, July 21, 1969; 62 minutes
    - Black Studies Faculty Meeting, October 10, 1970; 103 minutes
      The second half of this recording is damaged.
    - Man, Music accompanying dance performance, March 31, 1971; 49 minutes
    - Ain't Supposed to Die a Natural Death, Black Horizons Theater, ca. 1971; 88 minutes
    - The Black Terror, New York Shakespeare Festival, ca. 1971; 34 minutes
    - The Black Terror, New York Shakespeare Festival, ca. 1971; 62 minutes
    - House Rent composition, Pittsburgh Black Theatre Dance Ensemble, ca. 1971; 31 minutes
    - Pittsburgh Congress of African People Present Union of South Africa, ca. 1971; 131 minutes
    - Kuumba Theatre Workshop and McCoy Tyner at the Diplomat, June 1, 1972; 64 minutes
    - Music accompanying performance, Three Rivers Arts Festival, June 3, 1972; 37 minutes
    - Music accompanying performance, Three Rivers Arts Festival, June 5, 1972; 37 minutes
    - Black Happenin', Theatre Urge, October 20, 1972; 97 minutes
    - University of Pittsburgh Seminar on Jazz: A Tribute to the Late John Coltrane, October 20, 1972; 36 minutes
    - Amiri Baraka Lecture, University of Buffalo, ca. 1972; 47 minutes
    - Ruby Dee Lecture, University of Pittsburgh, ca. 1972; 78 minutes
    - University of Pittsburgh Jazz Concert, March 24, 1973; 108 minutes
    - Exposure I, Afro American Dance Center, May 19,1974; 46 minutes
    - Fall Term final performance, Afro American Dance Expression, December 6, 1974; 130 minutes
    - Bob LaPrince and Major Mason Discussion, March 30, 1975; 29 minutes
      The Pittsburgh Black Theatre Dance Ensemble, Bob Johnson, and fundraising for the African Heritage classroom at the University of Pittsburgh are disccused on a WEDO radio program.
    - Black Studies Commercial and Kuumba Theatre Workshop, ca. 1975; 12 minutes
    - Brief Portfolio, Pittsburgh Playhouse, ca. 1975; 37 minutes
    - Ceremonies in Dark Old Men, Theatre Urge, ca. 1975; 44 minutes
    - Conversation with Raymond Sawyer, ca. 1975; 39 minutes
    - Curtiss Porter, Ideologies in Education Lecture, ca. 1975; 109 minutes
    - Free Spirit Song, Pittsburgh Black Theatre Dance Ensemble, ca. 1975; 38 minutes
    - How Do You Spell Watergait?, Kuumba Theatre Workshop, ca. 1975; 46 minutes
    - How Do You Spell Watergait?, Kuumba Theatre Workshop, ca. 1975; 65 minutes
    - National Black Theatre Festival Discussion, ca. 1975; 191 minutes
    - Sun Ra concert, Atlanta, GA, ca. 1975; 66 minutes
    - American Fruit with African Roots, Theatre Urge, ca. 1976; 29 minutes
    - Norman Connors and Jean Carn Concert, University of Pittsburgh, April 2, 1976; 121 minutes
    - Hues of Langston, Theatre Urge, July 4, 1976; 60 minutes
    - The Money Ritual, Kuumba Theatre Workshop, November 8, 1976; 18 minutes
    - Black National Anthem and Brief Portfolio for Bicentennial, ca. 1976; 5 minutes
    - Bycenttenial, ca. 1976; 73 minutes
    - Bi Centennial Music, ca. 1976; 29 minutes
    - Black Dick For President, ca. 1976; 124 minutes
    - How do you Spell Watergait Rehearsal, ca. 1976; 28 minutes
    - Praises to the Root music, Nigeria, ca. 1977; 91 minutes
    - Fall Term final performance, Afro American Dance Expression, ca. 1977; 73 minutes
    - The Fabulous Miss Marie, ca. 1977; 51 minutes
    - Black Bart and the Sacred Hills Music, ca. 1977; 57 minutes
    - A Black Dirty Show, Theatre Urge, ca. 1978; 38 minutes
    - Ritual of Damballah, ca. 1978; 31 minutes
    - Baseball Ritual, Theatre Urge, ca. 1978; 17 minutes
    - Music accompanying workshop, The Wedding, Afro American Dance Center, ca. 1978; 15 minutes
    - Theatre Urge Trilogy, ca. 1978; 36 minutes
    - Black Mayonnaise, 1978; 30 minutes
    - Black Mayonnaise, 1978; 33 minutes
    - Afro American Culture Class, ca. 1978; 19 minutes
    - Afro American Dance Expression, ca. 1978; 19 minutes
    - Bitches Brew Rehearsal, ca. 1978; 43 minutes
    - Change Cycle, Afro American Dance Expression, ca. 1978; 29 minutes
    - Ego Trippin', Pittsburgh Black Theatre Dance Ensemble, ca. 1978; 33 minutes
    - Fire - Water - Earth - Air/Man, ca. 1978; 31 minutes
    - Fall Term, Afro American Dance Expression, ca. 1978; 35 minutes
    - Kuumba Theatre Workshop Music: Hollywood, ca. 1978; 19 minutes
    - Perpetual Motion rehearsal, ca. 1978; 16 minutes
    - WAMO Ballet, ca. 1978; 33 minutes
    - Sun Ra concert, Haag, Holland, July 14, 1979; 92 minutes
    - Winter Term, Kuumba Theatre Workshop, ca. 1979; 22 minutes
    - Fall Term final performance, Afro American Dance Expression, 1979; 32 minutes
    - Isis and Osiris Rehearsal, ca. 1980; 26 minutes
    - Louis Farrakhan Lecture, University of Pittsburgh, ca. 1980; 124 minutes
    - Black Bart and the Sacred Hills, LA Showcase, ca. 1980; 95 minutes
    - The Fabulous Miss Marie, Theatre Urge, ca. 1980; 22 minutes
    - Fall Term, Afro American Dance Class, ca. 1980; 91 minutes
    - Kuumba Disco, ca. 1980; 96 minutes
    - Miss Marie Disco, ca. 1980; 96 minutes
    - Sayonara Blues and The Fabulous Miss Marie, Theatre Urge, ca. 1980; 12 minutes
    - Sparkle Lipstick Disco, WAMO, ca. 1980; 45 minutes
    - Chocolate Puddin' Proposal, ca. 1981; 18 minutes
    - Fall Term, Afro American Dance Expression, ca. 1981-1982; 65 mins
    - Professor BonDe Drama Seminar, July 19, 1982; 92 minutes
    - Free Spirit Song and Afro American Dance Finals, ca. 1982; 126 minutes
    - Afro American Dance Finals, ca. 1982; 62 minutes
    - Dance Rehearsal, ca. 1982; 45 minutes
    - Malik's Song, ca. 1982; 24 minutes
    - Music accompanying Dance and Film Classes, ca. 1982; 129 minutes
    - Isis and Osiris, ca. 1982; 64 minutes
    - Kuumba Disco and AfroEurasian Eclipse, ca. 1982; 73 minutes
    - Excerpts from Brief Portfolio and Chairman Baraka, ca. 1982; 54 minutes
    - Black Studies Lecture, ca. 1982; 45 minutes
    - Dance Rehearsal Music, ca. 1982; 55 minutes
    - Pittsburgh Dance Council workshop, ca, 1982; 92 minutes
    - Free Spirit Song Music by Ken Addison, ca. 1982; 50 minutes
    - Free Spirit Song, 1982; 73 minutes
    - Production music, Jitney!, 1982-1983; 27 minutes
    - Afro-American Dance Finals and Earthquake Soundtrack, ca. 1982; 128 minutes
    - Fall Term, Afro American Dance Expression, ca. 1982; 70 mins
    - **Dance Lecture by Stevo Talks, ca. 1982; 122 minutes
    - Bessie Jones Interview, ca. 1982; 64 minutes
    - Ethel Ramos Harris Interview, ca. 1982; 114 minutes
    - Nigerian Dialogue, ca. 1982; 127 minutes
    - PCEP Board Meeting, ca. 1982; 120 minutes
    - Pedagogy of the Oppressed Seminar, ca. 1982; 121 minutes
    - Sing With the Birds, ca. 1982; 61 minutes
    - Dance Rehearsal, ca, 1982; 122 minutes
    - Sarah Yarbourgh Interview, ca. 1982; 40 minutes
    - Center for Cultural Studies Lectures, ca. 1982; 123 minutes
    - WAMO and Sarah LeGrand Interview, ca. 1982; 126 minutes
      Discussion held on Pittsburgh radio station regarding Bob Johnson's Black Happenin' dance production and University of Pittsburgh Black Activism week.
    - Choices II Soundtrack, ca. 1984; 12 minutes
      Choices II was directed by Bob Johnson and produced by Streetwise Productions. It aired in December 1984 and January 1985 on Pittsburgh Tele-Communications Inc.
    - Day of the Picnic and Ego Trippin', Afro American Dance Expressions, ca. 1984; 98 minutes
    - Songs for Little Black Boys Music, ca. 1984; 52 minutes
    - Rehearsal Music, Afro American Dance Expression, ca. 1985; 91 minutes
    - Nongogo Rehearsal, ca. 1985; 88 minutes
  - Film and Video, 1970-1985; 2.
    The types of recordings in this subseries include concerts, home movies, interviews, visuals accompanying performances, lectures, performances, rehearsals, and television broadcasts. These film and video recordings are arranged in chronological order.
    - Afro Set Party, ca.1970; 19 minutes
      Film recording includes footage of the Afro Set Party marching along a street, in a park, and in front of a school along with speakers and a fashion show at their headquarters. This recording has no audio.
    - Unidentified Dance Performances, ca. 1972; 35 minutes
      The recording quality is fair. Individual performances of dancers in a studio.
    - Unidentified Dance Performance, ca. 1972; 28 minutes
      Bob Johnson performance with other unidentified dancers on stage in a theater.
    - Black Horizons, WQED broadcast, ca.1973; 41 minutes
    - Bob Johnson Dance, April 6, 1974; 64 minutes
    - Kuumba Theatre Workshop, ca. 1974; 19 minutes
    - Pittsburgh Black Theatre Dance Ensemble, ca. 1974; 19 minutes
      First minute is end of a performance of The Ritual of Damballah. Recording cuts to another dance performance that includes Bob Johnson and other unidentified dancers.
    - The Rail, Kuumba Theatre Workshop, ca. 1974; 42 mins
    - Black Butter, Theatre Urge, February 1, 1975
    - Sun Ra Concert, September 2, 1975; 187 minutes
    - Reading and Discussion, Kuntu Writers Workshop, November 25, 1975; 65 minutes
      This recording of the Kuntu Writer's Workshop includes unidentified participants reading and discussing their work. August Wilson performs a scene written by him with two women. Following the readings, a discussion is led by Rob Penny.
    - The Fabulous Miss Marie, Theatre Urge, ca. 1975; 34 mins
      Recording includes footage from cast party.
    - In Dorm Living, Kuumba Theatre Workshop, ca. 1975; 19 minutes
      The theme for this iteration of Kuumba Theatre Workshop was dorm life at Pitt.
    - Performance, Afro American Dance Expression, ca. 1975; 19 minutes
    - Performance, Afro American Dance Expression, ca. 1975; 65 minutes
    - Performances, Pittsburgh Black Theatre Dance Ensemble, ca.1975; 25 minutes
      This film recording contains two unidentified performances by the Pittsburgh Black Theatre Dance Ensemble. It also includes footage of Johnson's family and an unidentified festival. This recording has no audio.
    - University Unity, Kuumba Theatre Workshop, ca. 1975; 33 mins
      The theme of this iteration of Kuumba Theatre Workshop was discrimination at the University of Pittsburgh.
    - Black Butter, Theatre Urge, January 31, 1976; 63 minutes
      This performance was staged at the Afro American Dance Center.
    - Performance, Theatre Urge, September 4, 1976; 66 minutes
    - The Money Ritual Performance, Kuumba Theatre Workshop, November 8, 1976; 48 minutes
      This is a recording of a Kuumba Theatre Workshop class performance in the William Pitt Union.
    - Compilation of Performances, ca. 1976; 49 minutes
      Dance performances in this recording include Raymond Sawyer Disco 76, Lecture Demo, The Bottle, American Fruit, and Sing with the Birds.
    - Black Expressions!, Pittsburgh Black Theatre Dance Ensemble and Oakland School of Theatre Dance, March 1977; 32 minutes
      Recording of Black Expressions performance at Carlow College's Antonian Theatre. Collaborative production of Pittsburgh Black Theatre Dance Ensemble and Cathy Powell's Oakland School of Theatre Dance.
    - Second Annual World Black and African Festival of Arts and Culture (FESTEC), 1977; 14 minutes
      Film recording was taken during the Second Annual World Black and African Festival of Arts and Culture (FESTEC). Footage includes dancers, including Bob Johnson, rehearsing, street performers with masks and puppets. Also footage of the people and environment of Lagos, Nigeria, where the festival took place. This recording has no audio.
    - Emotions, Kuumba Theatre Workshop, ca. 1977; 24 minutes
    - Fall Term Performance, Afro American Dance Expression, ca. 1977-1978; 33 mins
    - The Believers, Kuumba Theatre Workshop, ca. 1978; 50 minutes
      "The Believers" written by Margret Walker, student monologues and dancing. First minute and half blank.
    - Black Horizons, WQED broadcast, ca. 1978; 52 minutes
      Tape slightly damaged, but picture quality preserved. Cassette 6, Black Horizons Profile- Spotlight on Nate Smith. Bob Johnson dances. Last segment is "Gifted, Black, and in Pittsburgh."
    - Halloween Project, Kuumba Theatre Workshop, October 30, 1979; 28 minutes
      Recording cuts out at various moments. Performance at University of Pittsburgh about identity, music, race, slavery with costumes.
    - Fall Term final performance, African American Dance Expression, December 14, 1979; 65 minutes
    - Current Events, Kuumba Theatre Workshop, June 17, 1980; 37 minutes
    - Class Performance, Kuumba Theatre Workshop, ca. 1980; 33 minutes
      The picture quality of this recording is poor. The first two minutes are blank.
    - Pittsburgh's Dancin', WQED broadcast, ca. 1980; 60 minutes
    - Talkin Jazz, Pittsburgh Filmmakers, ca. 1980
      This show explores aspects of jazz outside of the club atmosphere, and provides footage of jazz musicians.
    - What's Your Sign?, Kuumba Theatre Workshop, ca. 1980; 63 minutes
      The theme for this iteration of Kuumba Theatre Workshop was astrology.
    - A Love Rap in Funky Town, Kuumba Theatre Workshop, July 30, 1981; 45 minutes
    - A Collage of Presentations, Kuumba Theatre Workshop, January 22, 1982; 28 minutes
    - Nothing Feels Better and Lady Beebop, March 29, 1982; 39 minutes
    - Performance, Kuumba Theatre Workshop, June 1, 1982; 14 minutes
      Directed by Ann Young, students perform simple choreography. Recording produced by Bob Johnson at the Webster Hall Studio, Warner Cable Corp. of Pittsburgh.
    - The African Footprint and African American Dance Expression, October 7, 1982; 58 minutes
    - The Undisco Fusion, Kuumba Theatre Workshop, November 30, 1982; 54 minutes
    - The Afro-American Dance Expression Technique and other recordings, ca. 1982; 61 minutes
      No sound in this recording. Multiple videos on this film including Theatre Urge performances, home movies, a slide show of photos, and city footage.
    - Blacks in Pittsburgh: A Chronology 1850-1950, ca. 1983; 34 minutes
      The theme for this iteration of Kuumba Theatre Workshop was the history of African Americans in Pittsburgh.
    - Ego Trippin' and Why Black Studies Creativity Workshop, August 2, 1984; 27 minutes
    - Myrenna Hawthorne Interview and Performance, ca. 1984; 15 minutes
    - It's Spooky Disco and Why Black Studies, January 28, 1985
      44 minutes